<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Docker | Ruan Bekker's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/categories/docker/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.ruanbekker.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-11-06T16:01:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.ruanbekker.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruan]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruan@ruanbekker.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Setup Alerting With Loki]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2020/11/06/how-to-setup-alerting-with-loki/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-06T15:13:53+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2020/11/06/how-to-setup-alerting-with-loki</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98380823-bd948880-2051-11eb-8ab4-c8d5f5d3e612.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>Recently Grafana Labs announced <a href="https://grafana.com/blog/2020/10/28/loki-2.0-released-transform-logs-as-youre-querying-them-and-set-up-alerts-within-loki/">Loki v2</a> and its awesome! Definitely check out their blog post on more details.</p>

<p>Loki has a index option called boltdb-shipper, which allows you to run Loki with only a object store and you no longer need a dedicated index store such as DynamoDB. You can extract labels from log lines at query time, which is CRAZY! And I really like how they&rsquo;ve implemented it, you can parse, filter and format like mad. I really like that.</p>

<p>And then generating alerts from any query, which we will go into today. Definitely check out <a href="https://grafana.com/blog/2020/10/28/loki-2.0-released-transform-logs-as-youre-querying-them-and-set-up-alerts-within-loki/">this blogpost</a> and <a href="https://grafana.com/blog/2020/11/04/video-top-three-features-of-the-new-loki-2.0/">this video</a> for more details on the features of Loki v2.</p>

<h2>What will we be doing today</h2>

<p>In this tutorial we will setup an alert using the Loki local ruler to alert us when we have a high number of log events coming in. For example, let&rsquo;s say someone has debug logging enabled in their application and we want to send a alert to slack when it breaches the threshold.</p>

<p>I will simulate this with a <code>http-client</code> container which runs <code>curl</code> in a while loop to fire a bunch of http requests against the nginx container which logs to Loki, so we can see how the alerting works. And after that we will stop our http-client container to see how the alarm resolves when the log rate comes down again.</p>

<p>All the components are available in the <code>docker-compose.yml</code> on my <a href="https://github.com/ruanbekker/loki-alerts-docker">github repository</a></p>

<h2>Components</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s break it down and start with the loki config:</p>

<pre><code>...
ruler:
  storage:
    type: local
    local:
      directory: /etc/loki/rules
  rule_path: /tmp/loki/rules-temp
  alertmanager_url: http://alertmanager:9093
  ring:
    kvstore:
      store: inmemory
  enable_api: true
  enable_alertmanager_v2: true
</code></pre>

<p>In the section of the loki config, I will be making use of the local ruler and map my alert rules under <code>/etc/loki/rules/</code> and we are also defining our alertmanager instance where these alerts should be shipped to.</p>

<p>In my rule definition <code>/etc/loki/rules/demo/rules.yml</code>:</p>

<pre><code>groups:
  - name: rate-alerting
    rules:
      - alert: HighLogRate
        expr: |
          sum by (compose_service)
            (rate({job="dockerlogs"}[1m]))
            &gt; 60
        for: 1m
        labels:
            severity: warning
            team: devops
            category: logs
        annotations:
            title: "High LogRate Alert"
            description: "something is logging a lot"
            impact: "impact"
            action: "action"
            dashboard: "https://grafana.com/service-dashboard"
            runbook: "https://wiki.com"
            logurl: "https://grafana.com/log-explorer"
</code></pre>

<p>In my expression, I am using LogQL to return per second rate of all my docker logs within the last minute per compose service for my dockerlogs job and we are specifying that it should alert when the threshold is above 60.</p>

<p>As you can see I have a couple of labels and annotations, which becomes very helpful when you have dashboard links, runbooks etc and you would like to map that to your alert. I am doing the mapping in my <code>alertmanager.yml</code> config:</p>

<pre><code>route:
...
  receiver: 'default-catchall-slack'
  routes:
  - match:
      severity: warning
    receiver: warning-devops-slack
    routes:
    - match_re:
        team: .*(devops).*
      receiver: warning-devops-slack

receivers:
...
- name: 'warning-devops-slack'
  slack_configs:
    - send_resolved: true
      channel: '__SLACK_CHANNEL__'
      title: ':fire::white_check_mark: []  '
      text: &gt;-
        
          *Description:* 
          *Severity:* ``
          *Graph:* &lt;|:chart_with_upwards_trend:&gt;&lt;|:chart_with_upwards_trend:&gt; *Dashboard:* &lt;|:bar_chart:&gt; *Runbook:* &lt;|:spiral_note_pad:&gt;
          *Details:*
           - *:* ``
          
           - *Impact*: 
           - *Receiver*: warning--slack
        
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, when my alert matches nothing it will go to my catch all receiver, but when my label contains <code>devops</code> and the route the alert to my <code>warning-devops-slack</code> receiver, and then we will be parsing our labels and annotations to include the values in our alarm on slack.</p>

<h2>Demo</h2>

<p>Enough with the background details, and it&rsquo;s time to get into the action.</p>

<p>All the code for this demonstration will be available in my github repository: <a href="https://github.com/ruanbekker/loki-alerts-docker">github.com/ruanbekker/loki-alerts-docker</a></p>

<p>The docker-compose will have a container of grafana, alertmanager, loki, nginx and a http-client.</p>

<p>The http-client is curl in a while loop that will just make a bunch of http requests against the nginx container, which will be logging to loki.</p>

<h2>Get the source</h2>

<p>Get the code from my github repository:</p>

<pre><code>$ git clone https://github.com/ruanbekker/loki-alerts-docker
$ cd loki-alerts-docker
</code></pre>

<p>You will need to replace the slack webhook url and the slack channel where you want your alerts to be sent to. This will take the environment variables and replace the values in <code>config/alertmanager.yml</code> (always check out the script first, before executing it)</p>

<pre><code>$ SLACK_WEBHOOK_URL="https://hooks.slack.com/services/xx/xx/xx" SLACK_CHANNEL="#notifications" ./parse_configs.sh
</code></pre>

<p>You can double check by running <code>cat config/alertmanager.yml</code>, once you are done, boot the stack:</p>

<pre><code>$ docker-compose up -d
</code></pre>

<p>Open up grafana:</p>

<pre><code>$ open http://grafana.localdns.xyz:3000
</code></pre>

<p>Use the initial user and password combination <code>admin/admin</code> and then reset your password:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98379039-7efdce80-204f-11eb-9c8a-3ed12a63cb14.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>Browse for your labels on the log explorer section, in my example it will be <code>{job="dockerlogs"}</code>:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98379172-ace31300-204f-11eb-8e6c-3cf073afe771.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>When we select our job=&ldquo;dockerlogs&rdquo; label, we will see our logs:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98379288-c71cf100-204f-11eb-911c-043a983bae6d.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>As I explained earlier the query that we will be running in our ruler, can be checked what the rate currently is:</p>

<pre><code>sum by (compose_project, compose_service) (rate({job="dockerlogs"}[1m]))
</code></pre>

<p>Which will look like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98379765-54604580-2050-11eb-9c90-5e0adf2bb586.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>In the configured expression in our ruler config, we have set to alarm once the value goes above 60, we can validate this by running:</p>

<pre><code>sum by (compose_project, compose_service) (rate({job="dockerlogs"}[1m])) &gt; 60
</code></pre>

<p>And we can verify that this is the case, and by now it should be alarming:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98379900-84a7e400-2050-11eb-87d0-ae52617d195e.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>Head over to alertmanager:</p>

<pre><code>$ open http://alertmanager.localdns.xyz:9093
</code></pre>

<p>We can see alertmanager is showing the alarm:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98380013-af923800-2050-11eb-8585-f7489bf722cb.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>When we head over to slack, we can see our notification:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98380158-de101300-2050-11eb-8d73-20828124fab5.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>So let&rsquo;s stop our http client:</p>

<pre><code>$ docker-compose stop http-client
Stopping http-client ... done
</code></pre>

<p>Then we can see the logging stopped:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98380907-e0bf3800-2051-11eb-99c3-b3b9ac22bba5.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>And in slack, we should see that the alarm recovered and we should see the notification:</p>

<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/98381360-722eaa00-2052-11eb-8bb4-07cdc8ffa7ee.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>Then you can terminate your stack:</p>

<pre><code>$ docker-compose down
</code></pre>

<p>Pretty epic stuff right? I really love how cost effective Loki is as logging use to be so expensive to run and especially maintain, Grafana Labs are really doing some epic work and my hat goes off to them.</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>I hope you found this useful, feel free to reach out to me on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/ruanbekker">@ruanbekker</a> or visit me on my website <a href="https://ruan.dev">ruan.dev</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setup a NFS Server With Docker]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2020/09/20/setup-a-nfs-server-with-docker/"/>
    <updated>2020-09-20T16:07:09+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2020/09/20/setup-a-nfs-server-with-docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this tutorial we will setup a <strong>NFS Server</strong> using <strong>Docker</strong> for our development environment.</p>

<h2>Host Storage Path</h2>

<p>In this example we will be using our host path <code>/data/nfs-storage</code> which will host our storage for our NFS server, which will will mount to the container:</p>

<pre><code>$ mkdir -p /data/nfs-storage
</code></pre>

<h2>NFS Server</h2>

<p>Create the NFS Server with docker:</p>

<pre><code>$ docker run -itd --privileged \
  --restart unless-stopped \
  -e SHARED_DIRECTORY=/data \
  -v /data/nfs-storage:/data \
  -p 2049:2049 \
  itsthenetwork/nfs-server-alpine:12
</code></pre>

<p>We can do the same using docker-compose, for our <code>docker-compose.yml</code>:</p>

<pre><code>version: "2.1"
services:
  # https://hub.docker.com/r/itsthenetwork/nfs-server-alpine
  nfs:
    image: itsthenetwork/nfs-server-alpine:12
    container_name: nfs
    restart: unless-stopped
    privileged: true
    environment:
      - SHARED_DIRECTORY=/data
    volumes:
      - /data/nfs-storage:/data
    ports:
      - 2049:2049
</code></pre>

<p>To deploy using docker-compose:</p>

<pre><code>$ docker-compose up -d
</code></pre>

<h2>NFS Client</h2>

<p>To use a NFS Client to mount this to your filesystem, you can look at <a href="https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2017/12/05/setup-a-nfs-server-on-a-raspberrypi/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">this blogpost></a></p>

<p>In summary:</p>

<pre><code>$ sudo apt install nfs-client -y
$ sudo mount -v -o vers=4,loud 192.168.0.4:/ /mnt
</code></pre>

<p>Verify that the mount is showing:</p>

<pre><code>$ df -h
Filesystem      Size  Used Avail Use% Mounted on
/dev/sda2       109G   53G   51G  52% /
192.168.0.4:/   4.5T  2.2T  2.1T  51% /mnt
</code></pre>

<p>Now, create a test file on our NFS export:</p>

<pre><code>$ touch /mnt/file.txt
</code></pre>

<p>Verify that the test file is on the local path:</p>

<pre><code>$ ls /data/nfs-storage/
file.txt
</code></pre>

<p>If you want to load this into other client&rsquo;s <code>/etc/fstab</code>:</p>

<pre><code>192.168.0.4:/   /mnt   nfs4    _netdev,auto  0  0
</code></pre>

<h2>NFS Docker Volume Plugin</h2>

<p>You can use a NFS Volume Plugin for Docker or Docker Swarm for persistent container storage.</p>

<p>To use the NFS Volume plugin, we need to download <a href="https://github.com/ContainX/docker-volume-netshare/releases" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">docker-volume-netshare</a> from their github releases page.</p>

<pre><code>$ wget https://github.com/ContainX/docker-volume-netshare/releases/download/v0.36/docker-volume-netshare_0.36_amd64.deb
$ dpkg -i docker-volume-netshare_0.36_amd64.deb
$ service docker-volume-netshare start
</code></pre>

<p>Then your <code>docker-compose.yml</code>:</p>

<pre><code>version: '3.7'

services:
  mysql:
    image: mariadb:10.1
    networks:
      - private
    environment:
      - MYSQL_ROOT_PASSWORD=${DATABASE_PASSWORD:-admin}
      - MYSQL_DATABASE=testdb
      - MYSQL_USER=${DATABASE_USER:-admin}
      - MYSQL_PASSWORD=${DATABASE_PASSWORD:-admin}
    volumes:
      - mysql_data.vol:/var/lib/mysql

volumes:
  mysql_data.vol:
    driver: nfs
    driver_opts:
      share: 192.168.69.1:/mysql_data_vol
</code></pre>

<h2>Thank You</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s it. Thanks for reading, follow me on Twitter and say hi! <a href="https://twitter.com/ruanbekker" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><strong>@ruanbekker</strong></a></p><p><a href="https://saythanks.io/to/ruan.ru.bekker@gmail.com" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><img src="https://svgshare.com/i/Pfy.svg" alt="Say Thanks!"></a></p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started on Logging With Loki Using Docker]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2020/08/13/getting-started-on-logging-with-loki-using-docker/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-13T13:39:28+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2020/08/13/getting-started-on-logging-with-loki-using-docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Logging with Loki is AMAZING!</p>

<p>In the past couple of months i&rsquo;ve been working a lot with logging, but more specifically logging with loki. As most of my metrics reside in prometheus, I use grafana quite extensively and logging was always the one that stood out a bit as I pushed my logs to elasticsearch and consumed them from grafana. Which worked pretty well, but the maintenance and resource costs was a bit too much for what I was looking for.</p>

<p>And then grafana released Loki, which is like prometheus, but for logs. And that was just super, exactly what I was looking for. For my use case, I was looking for something that can be consumed by grafana as a presentation layer, central based so I can push all sorts of logs, and want a easy way to grep for logs and a bonus would be to have a cli tool.</p>

<p>And Loki checked all those boxes!</p>

<div class="tenor-gif-embed" data-postid="7644619" data-share-method="host" data-width="100%" data-aspect-ratio="1.1971153846153846"><a href="https://tenor.com/view/oh-yeah-gif-7644619">Oh Yeah Parks And Recreation GIF</a> from <a href="https://tenor.com/search/ohyeah-gifs">Ohyeah GIFs</a></div>


<script type="text/javascript" async src="https://tenor.com/embed.js"></script>


<h2>What can you expect from this blog</h2>

<p>In this post will be a getting started guide to Loki, we will provision Loki, Grafana and Nginx using Docker to get our environment up and running, so that we can push our nginx container logs to the loki datasource, and access the logs via grafana.</p>

<p>We will then generate some logs so that we can show a couple of query examples using the log query language (LogQL) and use the LogCLI to access our logs via cli.</p>

<p>In a <a href="">future post</a>, I will demonstrate how to setup Loki for a non-docker deployment.</p>

<h2>Some useful information about Loki</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s first talk about Loki compared with Elasticsearch, as they are not the same:</p>

<ol>
<li>Loki does not index the text of the logs, instead grouping entries into streams and index those with labels</li>
<li>Things like full text search engines tokenizes your text into k/v pairs and gets written to an inverted index, which over time in my opinion gets complex to maintain, expensive to scale, storage retention, etc.</li>
<li>Loki is advertised as easy to scale, affordable to operate as it uses DynamoDB for Indexing and S3 for Storage</li>
<li>When using Loki, you may need to forget what you know and look to see how the problem can be solved differently with parallelization. Loki’s superpower is breaking up queries into small pieces and dispatching them in parallel so that you can query huge amounts of log data in small amounts of time.</li>
</ol>


<p>If we look at the <strong>Loki Log Model</strong>, we can see that the timestamp and the labels are indexed and the content of the logs are not indexed:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/cpr6n7.png" alt="loki" /></p>

<p>A <strong>log stream</strong> is a stream of log entries with the same exact label set:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/el6djk.png" alt="loki" /></p>

<p>For the <strong>storage</strong> side, inside each chunk, log entries are sorted by timestamp. Loki only indexes minimum and maximum timestamps of a chunk. Storage options support local storage, AWS S3, Google Cloud Storage and Azure</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/959pjw.png" alt="loki" /></p>

<p>For <strong>chunks and querying</strong>, chunks are filled per stream and they are flushed of a few criterias such as age and size:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/ekm8cy.png" alt="loki" /></p>

<p>And one of the most important parts are the <strong>labels</strong>, labels define the stream and therefore its very important.</p>

<p>High cardinality is bad for labels, as something like a IP address can reduce your performance a lot, as it will create a stream for every unique IP label.</p>

<p>Static defined labels such as environment, hostnames are good, you can read more up about it <a href="https://grafana.com/blog/2020/04/21/how-labels-in-loki-can-make-log-queries-faster-and-easier/">here</a></p>

<p>Here is a info graphic on how one log line can be split up into 36 streams:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/g119oq.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>So with that being said, <strong>good labels</strong> will be considered as cluster, job, namespace, environment, etc where as <strong>bad labels</strong> will be things such as userid, ip address, url path, etc</p>

<h2>Selecting logstreams with Loki</h2>

<p>Selecting logstreams, is done by using <strong>label matchers</strong> and <strong>filter expressions</strong>, such as this example:</p>

<pre><code>{job="dockerlogs", environment="development"} |= "POST" |~ "196.35.64.+"
</code></pre>

<p>Label Matchers and Filter Expressions support:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>=</code> Contains string</li>
<li><code>!=</code> Does not contain string</li>
<li><code>=~</code> Matches regular expression</li>
<li><code>!~</code> Does not match regular expression</li>
</ul>


<h2>Supported Clients</h2>

<p>At the moment of writing, loki supports the following log clients:</p>

<ul>
<li>Promtail (tails logs and ships to Loki)</li>
<li>Docker Driver</li>
<li>Fluentd</li>
<li>Fluent Bit</li>
<li>Logstash</li>
</ul>


<p>We will be going into more detail on using promtail in a <a href="">future post</a>, but you can read more up about it <a href="https://github.com/grafana/loki/tree/master/cmd">here</a></p>

<h2>Loki in Action</h2>

<p>Time to get to the fun part, clone my <a href="https://github.com/ruanbekker/loki-docker-nginx-example">github repo</a>:</p>

<pre><code>$ git clone https://github.com/ruanbekker/loki-docker-nginx-example
$ cd loki-docker-nginx-example
</code></pre>

<p>You can inspect the docker-compose.yml:</p>

<pre><code>$ cat docker-compose.yml
version: "3.4"

services:
  my-nginx-service:
    image: nginx
    container_name: my-nginx-service
    ports:
      - 8000:80
    environment:
      - FOO=bar
    logging:
      driver: loki
      options:
        loki-url: http://localhost:3100/loki/api/v1/push
        loki-external-labels: job=dockerlogs,owner=ruan,environment=development

  grafana:
    image: grafana/grafana:7.1.1
    volumes:
    - ./config/datasource.yml:/etc/grafana/provisioning/datasources/datasource.yml
    ports:
    - "3000:3000"

  loki:
   image: grafana/loki:v1.3.0
   volumes:
     - ./config/loki.yaml:/etc/config/loki.yaml
   entrypoint:
     - /usr/bin/loki
     - -config.file=/etc/config/loki.yaml
   ports:
     - "3100:3100"
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see loki will be the datasource where we will be pushing our logs to from our nginx container and we are defining our logging section where it should find loki and we are also setting labels to that log stream using <code>loki-external-labels</code>. Then we are using grafana to auto configure the loki datasource from the <code>./config/datasource.yml</code> section so that we can visualize our logs.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to define the logging section per container, you can always set the defaults using the <code>/etc/docker/daemon.json</code> by following <a href="https://grafana.com/docs/loki/latest/clients/docker-driver/configuration/#change-the-default-logging-driver">this guide</a></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s boot up our stack:</p>

<pre><code>$ docker-compose up
</code></pre>

<p>After everything is up, you should be able to access nginx by visiting: <code>http://nginx.localdns.xyz:8000/</code>, after you received a response, visit Grafana on <code>http://grafana.localdns.xyz:3000</code> using the username and password: <code>admin/admin</code>.</p>

<p>If you head over to datasources, you should see the loki datasource which was provisioned for you:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/tyn0ny.png" alt="loki-grafana" /></p>

<p>When you head to the left on explore and you select the loki datasource on <code>http://grafana.localdns.xyz:3000/explore</code> you should see the following:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/5kp07m.png" alt="loki-grafana" /></p>

<p>You will see that grafana discovers logstreams with the label <code>job</code> as you can see that our <code>job="dockerlogs"</code> can be seen there. We can either click on it, select the log labels from the left and browse the label we want to select or manually enter the query.</p>

<p>I will be using the query manually:</p>

<pre><code>{job="dockerlogs"}
</code></pre>

<p>So now we will get all the logs that has that label associated and as you can see, we see our request that we made:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/gra0oe.png" alt="nginx-grafana-loki" /></p>

<p>We can see one error due to the favicon.ico that it could not find, but let&rsquo;s first inspect our first log line:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/6dbuqn.png" alt="loki" /></p>

<p>Here we can see the labels assigned to that log event, which we can include in our query, like if we had multiple services and different environments, we can use a query like the following to only see logs for a specific service and environment:</p>

<pre><code>{job="dockerlogs", environment="development", compose_service="my-nginx-service"}
</code></pre>

<p>In the example above we used the selectors to select the logs we want to see, now we can use our filter expressions, to &ldquo;grep&rdquo; our logs.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say we want to focus only on one service, and we want to filter for any logs with GET requests, so first we select to service then apply the filter expression:</p>

<pre><code>{compose_service="my-nginx-service"} |= "GET"
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/vv609g.png" alt="loki-logs" /></p>

<p>As you can see we can see the ones we were looking for, we can also chain them, so we want to se GET&rsquo;s and errors:</p>

<pre><code>{compose_service="my-nginx-service"} |= "GET" |= "error"
</code></pre>

<p>And lets say for some reason we only want to see the logs that comes from a 192.168.32 subnet:</p>

<pre><code>{compose_service="my-nginx-service"} |= "GET" |= "error" |~ "192.168.32."
</code></pre>

<p>But we dont want to see requests from &ldquo;nginx.localdns.xyz&rdquo;:</p>

<pre><code>{compose_service="my-nginx-service"} |= "GET" |= "error" |~ "192.168.32." != "nginx.localdns.xyz"
</code></pre>

<p>Make two extra get requests to &ldquo;foo.localdns.xyz:8000&rdquo; and &ldquo;bar.localdns.xyz:8000&rdquo; and then we change the query to say that we only want to see errors and hostnames coming from the 2 requests that we made:</p>

<pre><code>{compose_service="my-nginx-service"} |= "error" |~ "(foo|bar).localdns.xyz"
</code></pre>

<p>If we expand one of the log lines, we can do a ad-hoc analysis to see the percentage of logs by source for example:</p>

<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/9ctz6d.png" alt="loki-logs" /></p>

<h2>LogCLI</h2>

<p>If you prefer the cli to query logs, logcli is the command line client for loki, allows you to query logs from your terminal and has clients for linux, mac and windows.</p>

<p>Check the releases for the latest version:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/grafana/loki/releases">https://github.com/grafana/loki/releases</a></li>
</ul>


<pre><code>$ wget https://github.com/grafana/loki/releases/download/v1.5.0/logcli-darwin-amd64.zip
$ unzip logcli-darwin-amd64.zip
$ mv logcli-darwin-amd64 /usr/local/bin/logcli
</code></pre>

<p>Set your environment details, in our case we dont have a username and password for loki:</p>

<pre><code>$ #export LOKI_USERNAME=${MYUSER}
$ #export LOKI_PASSWORD=${MYPASS}
$ export LOKI_ADDR=http://localhost:3001
</code></pre>

<p>We can view all our labels, let’s view all the job labels:</p>

<pre><code>$ logcli labels job
http://localhost:3001/loki/api/v1/label/job/values
dockerlogs
</code></pre>

<p>Let’s look at family apps nginx logs:</p>

<pre><code>$ logcli query '{job="dockerlogs"}'
http://localhost:3001/loki/api/v1/query_range?direction=BACKWARD&amp;end=1587727924005496000&amp;limit=30&amp;query=%7Bjob%3D%22dockerlogs%22%2C&amp;start=1587724324005496000
Common labels: {environment="development", owner="ruan", compose_service="my-nginx-service", job="dockerlogs", host="docker-desktop", compose_project="loki-nginx-docker"}
2020-08-13 17:08:40 192.168.32.1 - - [13/Aug/2020:15:08:40 +0000] "GET / HTTP/1.1" 200 612 "-" "Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10.15; rv:79.0) Gecko/20100101 Firefox/79.0" "-"
</code></pre>

<p>We can also pipe that output to grep, awk, etc:</p>

<pre><code>$ logcli query '{job="dockerlogs"}' | grep GREP | awk -F 'X' '{print  $1}'
</code></pre>

<p>Supported arguments:</p>

<pre><code>$ logcli query --help
usage: logcli query [&lt;flags&gt;] &lt;query&gt;


Run a LogQL query.


Flags:
      --help             Show context-sensitive help (also try --help-long and --help-man).
      --version          Show application version.
  -q, --quiet            suppress everything but log lines
      --stats            show query statistics
  -o, --output=default   specify output mode [default, raw, jsonl]
  -z, --timezone=Local   Specify the timezone to use when formatting output timestamps [Local, UTC]
      --addr="http://localhost:3100"
                         Server address. Can also be set using LOKI_ADDR env var.
      --username=""      Username for HTTP basic auth. Can also be set using LOKI_USERNAME env var.
      --password=""      Password for HTTP basic auth. Can also be set using LOKI_PASSWORD env var.
      --ca-cert=""       Path to the server Certificate Authority. Can also be set using LOKI_CA_CERT_PATH env var.
      --tls-skip-verify  Server certificate TLS skip verify.
      --cert=""          Path to the client certificate. Can also be set using LOKI_CLIENT_CERT_PATH env var.
      --key=""           Path to the client certificate key. Can also be set using LOKI_CLIENT_KEY_PATH env var.
      --org-id=ORG-ID    org ID header to be substituted for auth
      --limit=30         Limit on number of entries to print.
      --since=1h         Lookback window.
      --from=FROM        Start looking for logs at this absolute time (inclusive)
      --to=TO            Stop looking for logs at this absolute time (exclusive)
      --step=STEP        Query resolution step width
      --forward          Scan forwards through logs.
      --no-labels        Do not print any labels
      --exclude-label=EXCLUDE-LABEL ...
                         Exclude labels given the provided key during output.
      --include-label=INCLUDE-LABEL ...
                         Include labels given the provided key during output.
      --labels-length=0  Set a fixed padding to labels
  -t, --tail             Tail the logs
      --delay-for=0      Delay in tailing by number of seconds to accumulate logs for re-ordering


Args:
  &lt;query&gt;  eg '{foo="bar",baz=~".*blip"} |~ ".*error.*"'
</code></pre>

<h2>Thank you</h2>

<p>I hope this was useful</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Increase Performance With Your Ghost Blog on Docker]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2020/06/08/build-a-ghost-blog-with-nginx-cache-on-docker/"/>
    <updated>2020-06-08T23:28:07+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2020/06/08/build-a-ghost-blog-with-nginx-cache-on-docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://img.sysadmins.co.za/wngib2.png" alt="nginx-blog-ghost-caching" /></p>

<p>Nginx Caching + Ghost == Great Performance.</p>

<p>In this post we will build a nginx reverse proxy with caching enabled for our static content such as images, which will be our frontend and therefore we will have port 80 exposed, and run our ghost blog as our backend, which we will proxy traffic through from our nginx container.</p>

<h2>But why would you want caching?</h2>

<p>Returning data from memory is a lot faster than returning data from disk, and in this case where a request is being made against nginx, then it proxy passes the request to ghost, gets the data that you requested and returns the data to the client.</p>

<p>So for items that rarely changes like images, we can benefit from caching, so the images can be returned from the nginx service, where the first request will be made to ghost and then it will be loaded into nginx cache, so then the next time when you request the same image it will be returned from cache instead of making that same request to ghost again.</p>

<h2>Caching Info</h2>

<p>For this demonstration once we define the size of our chache which will be 500MB and we specify that if an object has not been accessed for 24 hours, we can expire the object from the cache.</p>

<h2>Nginx</h2>

<p>We will build our nginx container by adding our custom nginx config to our dockerfile.</p>

<p>Our <code>Dockerfile</code> will look like the following:</p>

<pre><code>ROM nginx:stable
ADD nginx.conf /etc/nginx/nginx.conf
</code></pre>

<p>Our <code>nginx.conf</code> configuration file:</p>

<pre><code>events {
  worker_connections  1024;
}

http {
  default_type       text/html;
  access_log         /dev/stdout;
  sendfile           on;
  keepalive_timeout  65;

  #proxy_cache_path /tmp/ghostcache levels=1:2 keys_zone=ghostcache:500m max_size=2g inactive=30d;
  proxy_cache_path /tmp/ghostcache levels=1:2 keys_zone=ghostcache:60m max_size=500m inactive=24h;
  proxy_cache_key "$scheme$request_method$host$request_uri";
  proxy_cache_methods GET HEAD;

  server {
    listen 80;

    location / {
        proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-For $proxy_add_x_forwarded_for;
        proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-Proto $scheme;
        proxy_set_header X-Real-IP $remote_addr;
        proxy_set_header Host $http_host;
        proxy_pass http://ghost:2368;
    }

    location ~* \.(?:css|js|ico)$ {
        proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-For $proxy_add_x_forwarded_for;
        proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-Proto $scheme;
        proxy_set_header X-Real-IP $remote_addr;
        proxy_set_header Host $http_host;
        proxy_pass http://ghost:2368;
        access_log off;
    }

    location ^~ /content/images/ {
        proxy_cache ghostcache;
        proxy_cache_valid 60m;
        proxy_cache_valid 404 1m;
        proxy_ignore_headers Set-Cookie;
        proxy_hide_header Set-Cookie;
        proxy_cache_use_stale error timeout invalid_header updating http_500 http_502 http_503 http_504;
        proxy_ignore_headers Cache-Control;
        add_header X-Cache-Status $upstream_cache_status;

        proxy_set_header Host $http_host;
        proxy_set_header X-Real-IP $remote_addr;
        proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-For $proxy_add_x_forwarded_for;
        proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-Proto $scheme;
        proxy_pass http://ghost:2368;
        access_log off;
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Then our <code>docker-compose.yml</code> where we will add our nginx and ghost container to run together:</p>

<pre><code>version: '3.4'

services:
  ghost:
    image: ghost:3.15.1
    container_name: 'ghost'
    environment:
      - NODE_ENV=production
      - url=http://localhost:80
    networks:
      - ghost
    volumes:
      - ghost_content:/var/lib/ghost/content/data

  proxy:
    build: .
    container_name: 'proxy'
    depends_on:
      - ghost
    ports:
      - 80:80
    networks:
      - ghost

networks:
  ghost: {}

volumes:
  ghost_content: {}
</code></pre>

<p>To boot our stack:</p>

<pre><code>$ docker-compose up
</code></pre>

<h2>Test Caching</h2>

<p>Once your containers are in a running state, open your browsers devloper tools and look at the networking tab, then access your ghost blog on <code>http://localhost:80/</code>, the first time a image is opened you should see the cache shows <code>MISS</code> when you refresh again you should see a <code>HIT</code>, which means that the object is being returned from your cache.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting the Correct Service Name in Datadog Logging for Docker Swarm]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2019/12/11/setting-the-correct-service-name-in-datadog-logging-for-docker-swarm/"/>
    <updated>2019-12-11T23:35:53+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ruanbekker.com/blog/2019/12/11/setting-the-correct-service-name-in-datadog-logging-for-docker-swarm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For some reason, when logging to datadog from your applications running on docker swarm, the service names in datadog appears to have the names on the docker image. The application talks to the datadog agent which runs in global mode on swarm.</p>

<p>Setting <code>DATADOG_SERVICE_NAME</code> or <code>DD_SERVICE_NAME</code> as environment variables on the swarm service has zero affect, as they keep showing the service name as the docker image name, as example:</p>

<p><img width="1268" alt="08496333-01C4-4492-807E-FAC40826AFDE" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70661591-49007080-1c6d-11ea-8230-0dbe086bd168.png"></p>

<p>If we inspect the tags, we can see that the docker image shows as the source and maps through as the docker service name. As you can see the swarm service name is what we want to be the service name (not alpine):</p>

<p><img width="1269" alt="783C6D52-62B2-4F2B-A6D4-28150CC58005" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70661651-65041200-1c6d-11ea-858b-90034099c319.png"></p>

<p>One way how to fix this is to setup a pipeline processor, head over to Logs -> Configuration:</p>

<p><img width="267" alt="93CEE277-55A6-4DE1-8AE6-A02C64B0ACAD" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70661767-adbbcb00-1c6d-11ea-8274-ad5da6ddfdd7.png"></p>

<p>Select &ldquo;Pipelines&rdquo; and add a new pipeline, select the filter <code>source:alpine</code> to limit down the results to the alpine image, and name your processor:</p>

<p><img width="763" alt="0BF3D6A6-9646-442D-A494-8DF489C5217F" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70661837-cdeb8a00-1c6d-11ea-8fb4-2c272fda596f.png"></p>

<p>Next add a new processor and set the type to remapper, select the tag group as &ldquo;swarm_service&rdquo; and set the attribute to service and name the processor:</p>

<p><img width="762" alt="C02092F4-0EEC-4AF9-9E2A-F7A126560CD8" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70662081-3a668900-1c6e-11ea-9ea9-9f80dfc669f3.png"></p>

<p>Add a new processor:</p>

<p><img width="1151" alt="5C2F7FB9-8948-4588-A283-86E94BC07513" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70661901-e6f43b00-1c6d-11ea-9dbc-8c4c3a24b51b.png"></p>

<p>Select a service remapper, set the attribute to service and name the processor:</p>

<p><img width="761" alt="852904AE-9395-4B4B-B1F4-54427D88C970" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70661986-0ab78100-1c6e-11ea-9edc-5fd748d73d0c.png"></p>

<p>Now when you go back to logs, you will find that the service name is being set to the correct service name in datadog:</p>

<p><img width="1159" alt="0F11DDC4-E99C-4A2F-B6AB-7409B4E7546C" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70662290-95987b80-1c6e-11ea-8d8c-bec4d44cde60.png"></p>

<p>When you inspect one of the logs, you will see that the attribute is being set to the log:</p>

<p><img width="633" alt="4B098970-6345-40B9-9F90-411D8FE6A9E6" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/567298/70662330-a9dc7880-1c6e-11ea-8b48-51900161cf01.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
